Hello friends, welcome back to True
Health Tuesday. My name is Maria Jose
Hmel and today we are doing our last
session of reversing
diabetes and other metabolic diseases. I
promised this was going to be a
four-part series and today we're doing
the last part. So if we if you're
joining today for the first time
um you can go back and watch the
previous three sessions um and we have
been covering not only diabetes but all
the related diseases all the related
conditions. So if you want to really
know more about it, I recommend you go
back and you will find out that diabetes
is connected to so many other things,
not just diabetes, but really the root
cause. So if you've been uh joining us
for the last three sessions, we've been
doing these every other week and you
have been uh finding so many interesting
things about how diabetes is connected
or really the root cause of diabetes is
really connected to so many other
things. These things don't happen in a
vacuum so to speak. they are connected
because these are metabolic conditions
uh that have the same root cause and
that's why uh when we fix our lifestyle
uh so to speak we connect we can fix
everything it's just like the same
medicine cures everything uh so it's
really interesting in that sense so I'm
so glad you're back um and uh I am happy
because we are completing a cycle But we
are really not done. Next time we're
going to continue talking about how we
can change our habits, how we can change
our lifestyle. And sometimes it seems
very difficult, but we can do it. Uh so
I will continue talking about that, but
we will close this four session cycle if
you will. So I'm very very um excited
about this because I think I think some
of these things will seem surprising to
you. So, right off the bat, I let you
know that these are surprising lifestyle
strategies so that you can uh let your
friends know uh let your uh uh go ahead
and share this uh link with your friends
because look, some of you might not even
know that these lifestyle habits, these
lifestyle strategies can actually change
help you um defeat these metabolic
conditions. And when I speak about
metabolic conditions, I mean
cholesterol, other lipids, uh,
hypertension, fatty liver, you know, all
the other things we've been talking
about for the last few weeks. That's
what I mean. Even um, weight,
overweight, and obesity. So, look at
the, uh, look at what it says right
here. Sleep,
stress management,
even fasting,
sunlight. By the way, uh Dr. Schwelt, I
know that he's done um other True Health
Tuesdays in the past and I know he will
be speaking soon and he talks a lot
about sunlight exposure and I'll mention
it briefly today because I know he'll
probably talk about it again if he
hasn't even he's probably done programs
about the this in the past. He'll
probably uh see him in his own channel,
YouTube channel. he can uh he's talked
about it in his videos. So, you can go
back to his YouTube channel and learn a
lot more about it. So, I'll just mention
it briefly today, but I will mention it
today. This could be surprising for a
lot of people and and I'll mention some
things about the microbiota. If you
don't know what it is, I'll talk about
it, so don't worry. So, these things can
be surprising for some people. So, go
ahead and share this link. tell your
friends uh so you can find out more how
these things that you are looking at
right now can actually help so much with
not just diabetes, pre-diabetes and
insulin resistance but all the other
conditions we've been talking about for
the last few weeks
to you. So, you know, the last few weeks
we've been mentioning about diet and uh
exercise, but it's not just that. Okay.
So, we're going to talk about how you
can actually have a perfect diet and do
all the exercise in the world. And what
if it's not enough? What if you're
perfect following a perfect diet and
what if you're doing all the exercise in
the world and it's not working? Well,
what if some of these things are not in
line? You know, what if what some of
these things that you're looking at
right here? What if you're not sleeping?
You know, what if that's what's not uh
working for you? What if that's what
needs to be fixed? So, that's what we're
going to be talking about. But before,
as always, we need to start with prayer.
So, before I forget, let's have a quick
word of prayer and then we'll get right
into it. So, let's pray. Dear heavenly
father, thank you so much for this
beautiful day and thank you for the
opportunity to have this um this online
meeting where we can talk about these
important topics about how to take
better care of our temple body that you
have given us. And please bless this
meeting, bless this presentation and
help it to go well and help this uh
presentation to get to all the people
that need to watch it, that need to
learn more about these important topics.
Uh and please bless every single person
that is connected tonight and that will
watch it later. Uh so that they will be
able to appreciate and learn more and
more and also share with other people.
We ask you for this blessing in Jesus'
name. Amen. Amen. Amen. All right. So,
as always, I want to make sure that you
know that this is meant to be 100%
educational, okay? This is not meant to
be medical advice. So make sure that
whatever you learn today that you will
discuss it with your doctor if you have
diabetes or you know if you have some
other condition and that oh somebody is
watching from New Brunswick. I hope I
pronounce it correctly from Canada.
Thank you. Thank you for connecting
today from Canada. I am so happy you're
with us.
So, as I was saying, make sure that if
you have diabetes, especially if you're
taking uh insulin or if you have uh high
cholesterol, if you're taking statins or
some other medication, if you're have
high blood pressure, if you're taking
blood pressure medications, etc. If you
have any of these conditions, if you're
taking medications, don't stop taking it
without the advice of your doctor. So,
everything we're presenting today is for
educational purposes. It's not meant to
be medical advice. Okay. Also, as you
know, I always say this, so if you're
connecting for the first time, you're
learning it or you're hearing this for
the first time. If you've uh heard me
say this before, this is just a uh
review. I always say the following.
Everything that I present, I always try
to go according to the Bible and spirit
of prophecy. as Isaiah 8 uh 8:20 says to
the law and the testimony if they speak
not according to this word is because
there's no light in it or light in them.
So that is my rule and so that's why I'd
like to say that as a disclaimer uh at
the beginning because I hope that
everything that I'm saying is according
to this uh Bible and the spirit of
prophecy. That's how I interpret Isaiah
8:20. And also I always present
scientific evidence. Uh and this is the
pyramid of the hierarchy of scientific
evidence. The reason why I present it is
because I want you to look at the bottom
of the pyramid. And the bottom of the
pyramid says expert opinion uh is at the
very bottom. So whenever you hear these
things on social media or the internet
and people uh just say opinions, they're
just stuff uh that could be
misinformation. Okay? Just look at what
you're hearing. And if it's just people
saying things, that doesn't mean it's
good evidence. Okay? When you look at
things on the internet or uh especially
nowadays, social media, a lot of it, by
the way, can be artificial intelligence.
Okay? So, we just can't just believe
everything we see. Okay? Make sure that
you're looking at things that are good
quality evidence. That's why I present
this to you to look at it so that it's
for your own benefit. And a lot of
people, you know, I've had my own um uh
videos on YouTube, my in my own channel,
and people tell me, "Why do you use so
much science? We have the Bible and
spirit of prophecy." Well, a lot of the
things that we present,
not everybody who watches it is a
believer in the Bible and the spirit of
prophecy. So, sometimes we need to use
something that people will actually, you
know, will believe in if they are not if
they're not Christians, right? And we
need to I think be uh have credibility
and also
if by if we follow our own rule my rule
uh is Isaiah 8:20 which says to the law
and the testimony and the testimony I
believe in the spirit of prophecy and
the spirit of prophecy says a knowledge
of science of all kinds is power and it
is the purpose of God that advanced
science shall be taught in our schools
as preparation for the work that is to
precede the closing scenes of Earth's
history which is right now. So I believe
it is very important that we present
solid scientific evidence especially
when we're talking to people who are not
believers. So oh I don't know how to
pres uh um pronounce your name Hiva I
don't know uh how to pronounce your name
but you say you're saying yes I like to
compare things too. Thank you very much.
Uh so anyway, you can read the other um
quotation here. It says, "A practical
knowledge of science of human life is
necessary in order to glorify God in our
bodies." And just to kind of review
things that I've said in the past, God
wants us to use common sense and he
wants us to be wise as serpents. He
wants us to be prudent and acquire
knowledge, to seek knowledge. Okay? So
this is review of things that I've said
in the past. I just want you to know
where I where I stand in those ter in
those uh things. Okay. But going back to
what we were talking about before in
terms of diabetes, pre-diabetes and
insulin resistance, I want you to know
that insulin resistance as we we've said
in the past is 100% reversible. And this
is the root cause of all the conditions
that we've talked about in the past. So
if you are joining us for the first
time, I recommend you go back to
presentation number one where we talk
about the root cause. In fact, you can
even go back further to my first
presentation that I did for true health
Tuesday which was 10 days to better
health. And that's when I actually even
talk more in detail about the root cause
of these conditions and that is insulin
resistance and how it starts in the
body. And insulin resistance is 100%
reversible you guys. That is great news.
It's 100% reversible. Completely
reversible. Pre-diabetes is also 100%
reversible by the way. 100% reversible.
And when we talk about how it is
connected to all these conditions, well,
okay, don't be discouraged because
pre-diabetes
and insulin resist uh resistance are
reversible. Now, type 2 diabetes, which
is the most common co uh type of
diabetes. There's not that's not the
only kind of diabetes as you know.
There's type one. There's gestational
diabetes which happens during pregnancy
goes away when the mom gives birth. But
did you know that 50% of moms develop
type 2 diabetes
after they give birth and some moms
within the f first five years after
giving birth by the way some moms later.
Uh so they are kind of connected. Type
two and gestational.
uh type one happens earlier in life
usually in childhood youth. That's an
autoimmune uh diabetes. Now there's 1.5.
I don't know if you remember that when I
presented I think I mentioned uh 1.5 is
also an autoimmune diabetes but happens
later in life. Okay. And now they're you
know now they're talking about type
three. What? Okay. I also mentioned that
before, but that's they're talking about
Alzheimer's disease actually because
they're saying that Alzheimer's disease
is actually maybe a metabolic disease
and happens because insulin resistance
happens in the brain too. Anyway, all
these things, but type two might not be
100% reversible. There's a small
percentage of people who maybe their
pancreas is not working that good after
many many years of overwork. Okay. So,
in a small percentage of cases, it might
not be 100% reversible. But that doesn't
mean it cannot improve.
Every single case can improve. Okay? So,
even if it's not 100% reversible, it can
still improve. Meaning, you don't have
to use as many medications. You don't
have to be uh getting worse and worse
and worse. In other words, you're the
disease doesn't have to be advancing so
much and getting more and more
complications. You don't have to die
early. Okay. So, you can still improve
and prolong your life. Okay? So, in
other words, by improving our uh habits,
we can in our lifestyle, we can improve
our health and prolong our life. When we
talked about the root cause of diabetes,
we talked about then the root cause of
these conditions which was the insulin
resistance. And if you remember that it
happened because not necessarily because
we eat only sugar, only excess of sugar,
but it was actually because there's
excess of do you see what's going on
over here? Fat,
excess of lipids inside of the cells.
All right? Inside of the cells. As you
see right here, those lipids inside of
cells are called intrammyiocellular
lipids. Remember that these lipids get
inside of the cells not just because we
consume excess sugars, which is what
most people think. Excess sugar causes
diabetes. That's not the only thing.
Excess sugars do become fat, but what
about excess fat?
It doesn't have to become anything. It's
already fat. So, it's actually easier
for the excess fat to just go right in
inside the cell. It doesn't be it
doesn't need to be transformed into
anything. It's already fat. It's
actually way easier for the fat to be
accumulated. In other words, and it's
the fat inside of the cells that blocks
the action of insulin. I'm just giving a
review. All of this has already been
said and Tyra says yes, fat. True. Okay,
so she already knows, right? She's
already heard this. Uh, and many of you
already have too because I've already
mentioned it in the past. So, it's the
fat that's blocking the action of
insulin. Now, the the extra sugar
becomes fat. The fat is already fat. So,
the additional fat, the extra fat we
consume in the diet goes right into the
cell and it blocks the action of
insulin. And that insulin is not working
properly. Therefore, the glucose is not
going inside the cell. That glucose
that's not going inside the cell stays
in the blood and that's the glucose
that's starting to circulate all over
the body and causing damage. Causing
damage for reals. Now, here's a more
anatomically correct picture. Okay, so
the the the picture before was just a
little cartoon. Here we see a more
anatomically correct in the sense that
what we're looking at here are muscle
cells. And on the top we see a nice
pretty
and normal muscle cell with no
additional adipose tissue and and
intramiocellular
fat, intramiocellular lipid droplets.
And when we see it down here in the
bottom, a lot of yellow. the all the
yellow is lipid lipid droplets
especially uh the very end over here in
the right because that's zoomed in now
what we're looking at is actually the
cells all the way zoomed in what we see
in the yellow there these are lipid
droplets in other words we're looking
actually the fat inside of the cell
that's the fat that's actually blocking
the insulin if the insulin is not
working,
then the glucose is not going inside of
the cell. When the glucose is not going
inside of the cell, it's staying
outside, therefore in your blood and
therefore when you go to the doctor, the
doctor measures your blood sugar, it
comes up high. Now, this is the picture
that I've been showing you over and over
again.
Look at these circles around the insulin
resistance. Do you see all these things?
Of course, you see first the types of
insulin. One, 1.5, pre-diabetes, type
two, gestational. These are all types of
diabetes. Okay. Okay. After you look at
all the types of diabetes, then we start
looking at things that are not diabetes.
Remember? Remember, right? Cancer.
What's cancer have to do with anything?
Well, it's connected because insulin
resistance is a risk factor
for cancer.
Cancer,
coronary artery disease, hypertension,
atherosclerosis. What's atherosclerosis
again? Atherosclerosis
is when the arteries become harder.
They start getting all that
cholesterol really inside of the artery.
They start getting clogged up really.
Then it says obesity. What
obesity? Because all that insulin that
is circulating. You have
hyperinsulinemia. Remember when the uh
when the insulin is not working properly
and now your pancreas is going well but
what's kind what's going on? What's
going on? Why is there so much sugar in
your body? And it starts pumping up more
insulin. Now you have hyperinsulinemia,
meaning you have more insulin than
normal. And now
all that insulin, did you know that
insulin is the growth hormone? By the
way, it's actually making you gain
weight. The insulin is making you gain
weight. I don't know if I've mentioned
this before, but here it goes. Insulin
makes you gain weight. In fact, people
who start injecting insulin when they
have to because they have diabetes not
under well under control. In fact, type
ones people who with type one they have
to and many many people in fact the
majority of people who have to start
injecting insulin can weigh can gain up
to 20 pounds in one month just from
injecting the insulin. So insulin will
make people store more fat and so it
leads to obesity. Says right there,
right? Obesity, high cholesterol,
fatty liver. We've mentioned this many,
many times. These are all things that
are complications of insulin resistance
that are not connected to diabetes
necessarily. I mean, they are connected,
but they're not diabetes. In other
words, uh fatty liver, PCOS. Do you know
what PCOS is?
Do you guys know what PCOS is?
Polycystic ovarian syndrome, ovary
syndrome. So, these are things that you
don't want to think it's connected to uh
insulin resistance. Well, it is. So, it
messes up your hormones. Alzheimer's
disease. We already mentioned some
people call it type three diabetes. Type
three.
Neuropathy. You know what that is,
right? Neuropathy.
Neuropathy is when the nerve endings,
especially the very tiny nerves in the
tip of your fingers or your toes, they
don't work properly anymore. So now you
start not feeling uh you lose kind of
the the sense uh then the sensibility
this you don't feel anymore some or it
maybe you feel like tingling
um and then sometimes we tell diabetics
not to walk barefoot for instance when I
used to work uh as a clinical
nutritionist and we would give
counseling to diabetics do not walk
barefoot at home Why?
Why? Because you would sometimes walk
barefoot, step on a piece of glass or a
nail or whatever, don't even feel it.
And what happens if you walk around,
walk on a, you know, a piece of step on
a piece of glass or whatever and not
even feel it? Well, you might have some
kind of injury or whatever or you some
kind of uh sore or something uh and then
it gets all dirty and then what happens?
It gets in uh infected. If it gets all
dirty, you don't even realize it.
And what happens to those infections?
They don't heal. They don't heal very
well because by the way, people with
diabetes have lower what?
Lower immunity. Therefore, their uh any
infections, they don't heal so well.
They their infections don't go away so
fast. They stay around. They stick
around longer. They have a cold, they
have flu, they have a a COVID infection,
they last longer. Okay. So, the
neuropathy, that's what it is. Their
nerve uh endings don't they basically
get damaged. Blindness.
Blindness. I met a 40year-old lady in a
town not too far from here. 40 year old
lady completely blind. At 40 years old
the retina detaches and uh that's what
happens when uh persons whose retina
detaches they don't see anymore. They
get they become blind. A kidney failure
as you know one of the main causes of
kidney failure and dialysis actually in
this country is due to type 2 diabetes
retinopathy. So we already talked about
that is a a problem with the retina and
the eye erectile dysfunction. There's
yet another thing that you don't think
is caused by insulin resistance but it
is. It could be. So all of these things,
do you see all of these things? You
think they're not related, but they
actually are. So some of these are
complications of insulin resistance that
are not even have to, you don't even
think they're not even diabetes. They're
not diabetes, but they are connected. So
that's why we've been talking about this
all these. So this is the fourth the
fourth session that we've been talking
about all these things, right? They're
all connected and that's why since
they're all connected, they have the
same solution. They have the same cure
in a way. I don't want to say the word
cure, but the ADA basically said it
could be cure. So, they said it, not me.
Now, the the second session we talked
about diet. I'm not going to talk about
diet again. If you want to go back, you
can watch the second program of the
four. We talked about which diet is best
and we explained why the whole food
plant-based diet, which by the way is
the same diet mentioned in the Bible.
Genesis 1:29. Oh, we have Please pray
for me. I'm on a 30-day sugar fast.
My first time. Denise,
yes, we will pray for you, everybody.
Everybody, we should all pray for Denise
because she's on a 30-day sugar fast. I
commend you for that, Denise. I think
that's a great idea. Wonderful. In fact,
I think we should all go on a permanent
sugar fast. I mean, and I and by sugar,
I mean processed sugar because uh you
can see right here in the picture, you
see, for instance, kiwi, mango. These
are fruits and God gave us Oh, oranges
also. There's some nice fruits over here
in this basket. God gave us uh fruits
that have sugar that is actually
uh that is actually mixed with fibers
and with antioxidants and and with um
vitamins and minerals and these sugars
are you're welcome Denise these sugars
are actually beneficial for us. So these
are god-given sugars in a way. But the
industrial sugars, the processed sugars,
those are highly
um refined and highly processed and have
nothing good for you. So I I
congratulate you for that. So good for
you. Okay. So that was key number one.
We already talked about it. And of
course the uh session after that we
talked about the physical activity. And
I hope you remember that we said that
everybody talks about walking. Walking
is great. I absolutely think everybody
should walk every day. In fact, and for
people who have diabetes, remember the
best time for walking. Remember, if you
don't remember, go back, watch it again.
Well, I'll just tell you the best time
for walking for diabetics is hopefully
after every meal. If you're not
diabetic, do it anytime, whatever time
of the day that will work for you. But
if you're diabetic, hopefully after
after every meal. But remember that
walking is not enough. Go back to that
to that uh program. Watch it again to
that uh uh video. Watch it again because
if you're not doing resistance exercise,
you are losing muscle. You are losing
it. If you're not using it, you're
literally losing it. All right? So watch
it again if you haven't watched it. So
those two keys are important, but it
might not be enough. As I said from the
beginning, in fact, you know, I'll just
tell you, I've seen at least
several cases. I'm not going to say one
or two. I'm just going to say several
cases. I remember one lady, I'm just
going to tell you one lady uh that I had
as a as a patient. In fact, when I used
to work at the clinic, and I remember
this poor lady, she her sugars were in
the 300 400 range all the time. And she
was an insulin of course and then and
then you know I started she started
being you know I I started counseling
she was a patient of the clinic and uh
and I would see her every like month or
whatever for in nutrition counseling and
I know she I I'm pretty sure she was
being honest. She was a very nice person
older older lady maybe in her 50s or or
I mean 60s or 70s and um and she just
seemed like a very honest person to me.
So, I think she was following the
nutritional counseling and I think she
was being honest and walking every day
and and then she would come back and her
sugars were just really bad and she was
on insulin, you guys. She was taking
medications. She was doing everything
and and her sugars were just not getting
any better at all. And I'm thinking
something's going on with this person.
Why is why is she even if she's trying
so hard with her diet, with her
exercise, even the insulin is not
working. What's going on with this
person? And so I and then, you know, I
started talking to her a little bit
more, a little bit more. I'm finding out
this poor lady is having a terrible time
with her husband. In fact, her husband
kicked her out of the room of their
bedroom. So, she's sleeping in the
living room and she says, you know, she
lives with a couple a couple of her sons
and they get up at crazy times in the uh
in the morning to go to work or
whatever. So, I'm like, "How many hours
of sleep do you get every night?" And
she's like, "Maybe three, maybe four."
And I'm like, "For reals, you only sleep
three or four hours a night?" And she's
like, "Yeah, sometimes even less." And
I'm just what?
What? I am petrified after what she
says. Like she's only getting three
hours of sleep, four hours of sleep,
sometimes even less. I'm thinking, no
wonder she can't control her blood
sugars, right? Like she's not getting
sleep and she's stressed out. And then
she starts telling me more and more
she's she has all these phobias. She has
all kinds of uh mental health issues,
right? She has crazy amounts of stress
with her son, with her uh husband. So
now I'm realizing and what I wanted to
show you here with this slide is
lifestyle medicine. So all these
different areas of lifestyle medicine.
I'm certified lifestyle medicine
professional, right? So I got certified
by the American College of Lifestyle
Medicine and we go way far above and
beyond just diet and exercise. There's
other important areas of lifestyle
medicine. And also if you are an
Adventist you know that we talk about
the eight principles of health uh which
go above and beyond just diet and
exercise. There's sleep, rest, right?
This is a part of the eight principles
of health or also called the eight true
remedies.
So sleep and rest uh trusting God which
I think is also uh the best way by the
way to control stress I think anyway. Uh
these are important parts of medicine.
They cure the body. If you're not
getting enough sleep,
you're probably even if you eat a
perfect diet and do all the exercise in
the world, your body is not healing. So,
that's what we're going to talk about
today because I think it's important to
keep this in mind that you can have the
perfect diet and the the perfect
exercise, but if you're leaving all
these other things out, if you're
neglecting these important aspects of
health, you might not be seeing the
results you want because of it. So,
let's talk about sleep for instance, and
I think it's surprising some of these
things that you that I'm going to show
you. For instance, it said it talks
about in this uh one study. It says role
of sleep in the regulation of what? Look
at what it says right here uh right
here. Role of sleep duration
in the regulation of glucose. What?
Glucose metabolism
and appetite. H
sleep duration. Oh wow, that's
interesting. Okay, let's look at what it
says more in detail. So, it says right
here, experimentally induced sleep loss.
Tyrus says yes. Okay. Uh experimentally
induced sleep loss in healthy
volunteers. Look at what it did. Okay.
So, these people basically took a a
bunch of volunteers, healthy volunteers,
and they deprived them of sleep to see
what happened. What did it do? It
decreased insulin sensitivity. Okay. So
they started experimenting
insulin resistance. That's what started
happening. That's what it means when it
says decreased insulin sensitivity.
Okay. Without adequate compensation and
beta cell function. What does that mean?
Beta cells are the ones in your
pancreas. In other words, they saw
insulin resistance and the pancreas
wasn't compensating for it. That's what
it says.
Resulting in what?
Impaired glucose tolerance.
Impaired glucose tolerance means the
glucose numbers started going up
and increased diabetes risk.
This is just from lack of sleep. in
healthy volunteers.
So then it says lack of sleep also down
regulates
the satiety hormone leptin.
I'm going to break I'm going to repeat
this. Okay, this is very important.
Please pay attention. Open up your ears
and your eyes.
Lack of sleep also downregulates that
means decreases
the satiety
hormone leptin.
It decreases your satiety you guys.
You're going to be hungrier
when you do not sleep. You're going to
be hungrier.
Upregulates.
What does that mean? upregulate. It
elevates
the appetite stimulating hormone grein.
Double whammy. You're going to
downregulate, you're going to decrease
the satiety hormone and you're going to
increase the appetite stimulating
hormone. This is a double whammy,
appetite dysregulation.
So that increases hunger and food
intake.
Do you see what's going on here?
Do you see what's going Did you know
that lack of sleep did this?
If you didn't know, now you do. So if
you're not sleeping, you're messing up
your insulin sensitivity and now you're
eating more.
You're hungrier.
Wow. Wow. I hope I hope you're paying
attention. All right. Okay. Here's
another one. Metabolic consequences of
sleep and sleep loss. Well, what could
be the metabolic consequences of sleep
and sleep loss? Okay, here it is clear
that chronic sleep deprivation. Oh, I've
heard some people, you know what? Some
people have told me this. I am okay with
sleeping four hours a night. I'm totally
okay with it. My body is totally used to
it now. Or really, is it? Look at what
it says right here. It is clear that
chronic sleep deprivation, by chronic
sleep deprivation, they're not talking
about four hours, by the way. They're
saying less than six. That's chronic
sleep deprivation. Less than six.
Chronic sleep deprivation has
deletterious. That means negative
effects
on carbohydrate
metabolism.
Carbohydrate metabolism, glucose
And is associated with an increased risk
of what? What does it say?
Diabetes.
Alter levels of hormones central to
what? You guys look at the words. alter
levels of hormones central to
appetite
regulation
such as the two we just read. Leptin and
grein. Leptin suppresses appetite and
grein stimulate appetite. So these are
like opposite, right? They work kind of
together.
So they both get dis disregulated
occur in sleepdeprived individuals and
consistent with this neuroendocrine
disregulation of hunger and appetite a
large number of epidemiological studies
have identified
short sleep duration as a puditive novel
risk factor for weight gain and obesity.
What this is saying you guys is that
when people do not sleep enough, it has
been found in large epidemiological
study meaning population studies
that lack of sleep causes weight gain
and obesity. You guys, that's basically
what this is saying. And how does it do
it? By disregulating our appetite, which
how? By disregulating our hormones
that regulate our appetite. That's
what's happening. We don't realize it,
you guys. You don't notice. You don't
know why you're hungry here. Well, it's
happening without you really noticing.
You're just hungry here. It's because
your hormones are messed up by not
sleeping.
Now what this other study shows is that
when they have done these programs that
are called sleep extension programs
basically
programs that teach people better habits
uh so that they can sleep more. So they
teach you basically, okay, uh, take a
nice warm bath before going to sleep.
Turn off the lights to, you know, like
the lights that are on the ceiling.
Don't turn them on like turn on the the
lights that are like on your on your uh,
table by your bedside. Uh, don't use
screens at night, especially blue
lights. Uh, don't watch TV or use your
phone. These are sleep hygiene. So just
look it up. use your uh uh search engine
and look up sleep hygiene
and you can find all these different
habits that you can start uh uh adopting
basically to get better sleep. So this
is this is what's called sleep
extension. Uh so what they're doing in
this study is they're teaching people
these better habits and what they found
is that with these sleep extension
programs, people who have followed it,
they actually improve their insulin
sensitivity.
So people who sleep better
improve their insulin sensitivity. In
other words, they decrease
their insulin resistance.
Better sleep,
better insulin sensitivity, you guys. It
works hand in hand. Isn't that
interesting?
Wow. So Denise says, "I knew about the
heart, but wow, it makes you hungry."
Yes. Yes, it makes you hungry.
Would you know? Okay. So, in other
words, when you when you now starts to
sleep better, now your insulin starts to
work better because they're connected.
And in this other study, people with
sleep apnea. Okay, so when you have
obstructive sleep apnea and type 2
diabetes,
now they found that when that is
treated, it actually helps with glycemic
control. So again, there's a connection
between between the control of glucose
and sleep. So this is just a
confirmation of that. I'm just showing
you more and more um evidence of the
connection between sleep and glucose
control. So people with sleep apnnea and
type two diabetes, sure enough, once
they started sleeping better because
they controlled their sleep apnnea,
their glucose control improved. Tada.
Same thing here. CPAP therapy with sleep
apnnea, type two diabetes improves
glycemic control during sleep.
More proof of that. Interesting, right?
So there's more and more connection. So
I just wanted to show you that you guys.
So interesting, surprising. I hope I
hope some of you have learned the
importance of sleep especially when it
has to do with glucose control and
insulin resistance. So for people who
are having a hard time and even if
you're not having a hard time, everybody
needs to sleep. Everybody needs to sleep
is one of the true remedies. I don't
know if you have read that quote in
Ministry of Healing. I think it's page
89 if I don't if I'm not mistaken. If
you haven't read the book Ministry of
Healing, I recommend it. You can read it
for free. You can download in your
phone. Where's my phone? Right here.
Download it in your phone for free. And
honestly, it's one of the most wonderful
blessings in the world. You can read it.
And in that uh quote where it lists all
the eight principles of health at the
end it says these are the true remedies
true remedies and one of them is rest
and by rest we mean the daily rest the
eight hours that we all need our bodies
at least seven you guys everybody it
varies from person to person some people
might be okay with seven seven and a
half some people may need eight some
people may need eight and a enough. But
everybody needs at the very least seven.
I don't think people can do very well
with less than seven honestly. Uh but
some people may need eight and some
people may need a little bit more.
Whatever. But we need all to sleep. We
we're not made to be awake so many hours
that you can only be okay with four
hours. That's not that's just not right.
Uh our bodies rejuvenate re that repair
tissues. Did you know that your brain
flushes out toxins at night? By the way,
this is called the glimpmphatic uh uh
system. At night, your brain flushes out
toxins, but that only happens at night.
By the way, this is something people
always ask me in connection to
intermittent fasting. If you have a late
dinner, let's say you eat at 8:00 p.m.,
go to sleep at 10:00. There's zero ways
that that dinner was already digested by
the way you go to by the time you go to
sleep. So that digestion has not been
completed. Therefore, you go to sleep.
Digestion continues overnight.
Digestion takes a lot of energy. So
while you're sleeping, a lot of energy
is still being used by digestion, the
digestive process. Therefore, all the
energy that should have gone to the
repair of tissues, the detoxification
and all these different things that have
to do with repair, rejuvenation and
detoxification, all these different
things and healing is not happening
because all that energy is going into
digesting still. So proper healing,
proper recover, proper detoxification is
not happening
if you eat dinner late.
You have to eat earlier. If you're going
to sleep with food in your stomach, the
energy that's supposed to be be used for
all the proper things that are supposed
to be happening during the night are not
happening. Just saying.
Okay, next thing is what happens with
stress? How does stress um affect our
levels of blood sugar? How stress affect
uh insulin resistance? You're welcome,
Denise, for the information. You're
very, very welcome. Okay, so let's go to
stress. How does stress affect
insulin resistance, blood sugar, etc.
Okay, well, look at this. Stress and
hypoglycemia.
What does stress do? Well, it elevates
the hormone that you probably already
heard a million times. There's a hormone
that has to do with stress. So,
basically, our bodies were made so that
if you're walking around in the jungle,
in the woods, let's say, uh, and you
encounter a big bear, what happens? What
happens if you go hiking in the woods
and all of a sudden you see a mountain
lion or a big bear? What do you need to
do? Well, let's say you're in the
jungle, you see a lion. Well, maybe you
need to run. For that, you need a lot of
energy. Okay? So, that stress
uh provokes a spike in cortisol. And
cortisol makes your blood sugar go up
because you need energy. You need energy
to be alert. You need energy for maybe
running and get out of the way so that
you are not eaten by a big lion. Um
that's basically why you need more sugar
when you're stressed out. Right
today,
uh 21st century, we're not being chased
by lions. We're not being chased by
bears or tigers or any of those things.
So when we're stressed, it's not because
we're in a situation where we have to
run necessarily for our lives.
Instead, we're more like chronically
stressed
in a sedentary
life, right? In context of sedentary
lifestyle. And so this kind of stress is
not good and is actually hurting. This
high amounts of cortisol is actually
causing
uh chronic diseases such as diabetes,
myioardial inffection. What is that? A
heart attack. Uh so these high levels of
cortisol are actually leading to chronic
diseases. And so that's what stress is
doing to us. Now, in this study that I
just showed you, there's this graph,
this graphic, sorry, this graphic. And
it's interesting because it's showing
here the stress up on top. Of course,
this is a picture of the brain. All
kinds of very interesting and intricate
uh connections, right, between stress
and look at right here, inflammation. In
fact, I found this grow I found this
study when I was back in 2020 when we
were all online. I was doing a lot of
presentations online about the immune
system actually and I was doing a
presentation. A lot of people were
asking me for this presentation on the
eight ways to improve your immunity. And
I found this study that talks about
stress and how stress actually increases
inflammation as you can see right here.
And you can see that stress increases
inflammatory cytoines, chemocines, and
other molecules that have to do with
inflammation. It increases inflammation.
And down at the bottom it says that this
has to this actually can elevate the um
the risk for infe infections because
later actually in this same study
there's a whole table that talks about
how this stress can actually reduce the
um some of these um some of the immunity
some of the imu some of parts of the
immune system. Actually if you can read
right here a lot of the in the table
talks about how it the different parts
of different stress different types of
stress actually reduces immunity but
also in the yellow I actually
highlighted that it increases something
called C reactive protein which is a
marker for inflammation. So this is
connected the stress, the inflammation
and the reduction of the immune system.
It's all connected. So unfortunately all
of this also can lead to a uh increase
the increase in inflammation can also
lead to chronic diseases and a reduction
in in the immune system is really bad
for diabetics as you know because people
with diabetes who have high blood sugar
and uh have reduced immunity as we said
before people with diabetes as you
probably know if they get any cut
anything like that especially especially
in the feet or any other place like
that. If it doesn't heal and if it leads
to an infection that doesn't heal, it
doesn't heal. Doesn't he? Unfortunately,
I have met many people who have had to
have fingers or worse yet toes or part
of their feet amputated because of the u
the infections not healing. So bad for
the immune system. It's bad that the
immune system is lowered like that
because of stress. So, managing stress
says this uh study right here improves
long-term glycemic control in type 2
diabetes. In fact, you can read right
here in the conclusion. It says current
results indicate that cost effective
group stress management program in realw
world setting can result in clinically
significant benefits for patient with
type 2 diabetes. Stress management can
lead to realworld results. In other
words, can lead to significant benefits
of glucose control. just stress
management. By the way, uh it has been
found that people who are chronically
stressed or even in uh types of anxiety
just doing deep breathing. Did you know
just deep brea just stop and do deep
breathing exercise and by deep breathing
you count to six
and just breathe in counting to six and
then breathe out counting counting to
seven. So breathing six and breathe out
to seven and just repeat that uh five to
10 times and that alone can bring down
your even your blood pressure. uh and
your anxiety in just like five minutes.
So that that's that alone is a very good
exercise. But also going out for walks,
being surrounded with green, the green
color seems to be very beneficial. I
think that's by nature because God made
it like like that. But going out to
places where there is a lot of green or
um just sound of water if you can go to
a place with a river or the ocean or a
lake uh just going out to nature can
also be very very beneficial. Of course
prayer and I'll show you actually. So
here's deep breathing. And it says right
here, the results obtained from the
present research support the possibility
that deep breathing technique is capable
to induce an effective improvement in
mood. So people with depression, anxiety
uh and stress both in terms of
self-reported evaluation and objective
parameters such as heart rate can bring
down heart rate and salivary cortisol
levels. So it can bring down both
cortisol and uh and heart rate. So
that's very important. But look so so no
number one breathe uh breathe deeply.
Okay? So do the deep breathing
exercises. But look at this you guys.
This is a scientific uh study. I'm not
making it up. It says spirituality
moderates the effects of stress on
emotional and physical adjud adjustment.
And it says right here in the abstract,
the results showed that spirituality
buffered the adverse effects of stress
on adjustment controlling for the use of
various coping strategies. In other
words, even these uh journals are
showing that people who have a spiritual
life can have better stress management.
So just having a spiritual life, prayer,
um maybe reading a your Bible, that kind
of thing can help you reduce your
stress. I believe that trust in God. You
know how we have the remedies, the eight
true remedies. Trust in God.
Number one, stress management. That's my
opinion. That's my humble opinion, but
it's it's right there, right? I think
it's given to us by God. The true
remedies in number one stress
management, trusting God. Okay. I want
to mention you guys the interesting
benefits of intermittent fasting for
diabetes, pre-diabetes and IR means
insulin resistance. I don't know how
many of you know because I want to
mention this because when I used to work
at the clinic way back then especially
back then everybody was telling
diabetics that you had to eat six times
a day. I don't know if you remember
this. Now it's not so much, but I'm
telling you, 10 years ago, everybody was
telling diabetics they had to eat the
three meals plus the three snacks or
else, oh my goodness, your blood sugars
were going to be out. Oh, those so
terrible. So, you had to had to had to
eat six times a day every two hours. So,
it was just the mantra. Everybody had to
do it. And you know, some of us who have
been reading the uh the writings of the
spirit of prophecy and we we know that
eating two times a day is even better
than three according to the writings of
the spirit of prophecy. And we're
looking at this going, "Wait a minute,
six times a day." It's like, what?
That's not even close to the two times a
day. Like what in the world? Uh so but
then now science has vindicated I think
in my view has vindicated
uh
what has been revealed
so long ago because science ultimately
always reveals truth always science
always vindicates truth in my view okay
so I just want to show you something
first of all let's clear up What's
intermittent fasting? Because there's a
lot of different kinds of intermittent
fasting. You probably you probably heard
the term intermittent fasting, right?
You probably have or at least fasting.
Fasting has been done for millennia.
Thousand in fact from before Christ.
The Greeks did it. I mean, the Bible has
been done. Of course, it's been
mentioned uh from the Old Testament. uh
but this has been done for thousands of
years. Now more recently we hear
intermittent fasting but there's
different kinds. So we hear of alternate
date fasting. So that means you fast one
day and then another day you don't and
then another day you do.
You can fast a whole day or part of the
day. But there's another kind of fasting
called timerestricted
feeding.
Timerestricted feeding means you eat for
a window of time. That could be eight
hours. That could be your eating window
or it could be 6 hours or it could be 10
hours. And then the rest of the day, the
rest of the 24 hours you fast. So that's
what timerestricted feeding means. It
means you dedicate six or eight hours to
eating and the rest of the day is
fasting. That's what timerestricted
feeding means. Okay. So, which one is
better? Which one is best? Well, let's
see.
Most people are doing this inter uh this
timerestricted eating or type restricted
feeding.
But
if you Google intermittent fasting,
everybody is doing or most people are
doing the 168.
And this is what they're doing right
here. They're getting up.
They're skipping breakfast.
Most people are skipping breakfast and
they're starting their eating window at
noon, more or less. Look at what they're
doing. Skip breakfast, start to eat at
noon, and they eat until 8, more or
less. And then they they start their
fast and they go overnight
until 6:00 in the morning or whatever.
and then they skip breakfast and they
continue their fast until noon.
That is the most popular nowadays that I
have seen. I don't know about you guys.
What have you seen? What have you
noticed? What's the most popular type of
intermittent fasting?
Have you fasted? By the way, if you
fasted, put it in the chat. What kind of
fasting have you done? And what kind of
fasting do you think is the most popular
kind? because this is the kind that I've
noticed anyway. And what do you think?
What do you think is best? Here's
another one. So, this is just what I've
searched, okay? Just by looking, just
Google intermittent fasting.
This comes up. Look at this. Here's
another example. 6:00 a.m. you wake up.
At 7:00 a.m. you drink tea, presumably
with no sugar, right? Because you're
still fasting. At 9:00 a.m., you drink
more tea with no sugar, probably. Look
at what time you eat your first meal. 12
noon. That's your first meal. At 400
p.m. you work out. 6:00 p.m. Second
meal. Big meal. Oh, look. Big meal at 6
p.m. Oh, look. 8:00 p.m. late snack.
And at 10 p.m. you go to sleep.
See? Okay. Here's another one.
Intermittent fasting. fasting window.
See, same thing. Same thing you guys.
This is the most popular that I have
noticed. What have you noticed? Put in
the chat if you noticed anything
different. But this is what I have
noticed. This is the most popular type
of intermittent fasting. What do you
think?
Is this the most Is this the healthiest?
Well,
look at this.
Look at this right here.
Well, the top we have three clocks.
Okay, we have three clocks or three
different ways you can do this.
The top says add libitum. Ad libbitum.
Do you see the very top?
Ad libitum means eat whatever you want
at whatever time. There's no fasting
here. Do whatever. which is the American
way or you know just the western way
meaning eat whatever at whatever time.
Well
that leads to an increase in chronic
diseases. Do you see that right there?
It whatever at whatever time no no uh no
restrictions
that leads to an increase in chronic
diseases.
But look at the middle. Well, no. Let's
skip the middle. Let's go down to the
bottom. The bottom says delay. See that?
The word delay and then TR. Well, TR
means timerestricted eating. As we
mentioned before, this is when you pick
a window of eating. And the delay
timerestricted eating is what I was
showing you. You delay your first meal
to noon. For instance, just to give you
an example, which is the most common,
you delay the first meal until noon and
then you eat until 8:00 p.m. That's the
delay timerestricted eating. And then
you see a big mark question mark. Why
the big question mark?
Well, because
the data has not really showed a
consistent
uh result in reducing risk of chronic
condition or chronic diseases or weight
loss. Some people lose weight, not
everybody.
In some studies, they've shown decrease
and risk uh risk of chronic diseases.
Not every single study has shown
benefit. That's why big question mark.
So you see that the one in the middle
says early timerestricted eating. What
does that mean? You do not delay your
first meal. You eat it when you get up.
You don't delay it. You eat early.
meaning you get up, you have your
breakfast, let's say 8:00 a.m.
breakfast, then you eat lunch, maybe you
have a six hour in between those two
meals. Let's say you have 2:00 p.m.
lunch, late lunch,
and that's it for your eating window. Or
maybe you have an 8 hour eating window.
You have a 12 a 12:00 p.m. lunch and a
400 p.m. early dinner or whatever. So
that's it. That's your eight hour window
and that's it. And then the rest of the
day it's a fast. And so overnight you
fast and the evening you're not eating
either.
That's early timerestricted eating. And
look at what it leads to. It leads to a
decrease. The arrow is going down and
it's consistent. The data in the
literature is consistent. It leads to
consistent lowered risk of chronic
diseases and most people lose weight
consistently. It's not a big question
mark like the delayed
version of it. The literature is very
very consistent like the early
timerestricted eating always hardly ever
is mixed like this always very very
consistently leads to a um a decrease.
So that's what I want to show you. Look
at this in in relation to insulin. Oh,
sorry about the red lines. I want it
wanted to be underlined but instead I
moved it and now it shows like it's
crossing it. It's not supposed to be
crossed. It's supposed to be underlined
it. Um, early timerestricted feeding or
eating, either way. Sometimes it says
feeding or timerestricted eating. It's
supposed to be underlined. Improves
insulin sensitivity. All right. Improves
insulin sensitivity.
Blood pressure. Oxidative stress. Even
without weight loss, even if you're not
losing weight, even if you're eating a
bunch of calories, you're still
improving your insulin sensitivity and
blood pressure and oxidative stress.
meaning you're bringing down
inflammation. Um so always is I mean
that the the the literature is
consistent
uh with this type of uh early time or
intermittent fasting. I wanted to show
you here the the plate with the times,
right? So the one in the left basically
the most common eating pattern for the
western world. I wanted to include
Canada because it's not just Americans
is Canada, Australia, Europe. Most
people eat just whatever time. Um and
compare that to the one on the left
early time early time restricted eating.
And that's when you eat early. So you
get up, you eat. In this case, they
stopped eating at 2 p.m. In this study,
they stopped eating at 2 p.m. So, the
extended fasting is quite long. It's
like 18 hours.
But look at what it what it did down
here at the bottom. You see the results.
Uh the insulin after meals, that's what
postprandial that word postandial means.
After meals, the insulin required after
meals went down because
your insulin sensitivity goes up,
meaning you need less insulin. You're
most sensitive to insulin. Therefore,
you need less of it because your beta
cell function is better. Beta cells are
the cells in your pancreas that make
insulin. That's what that means. So,
your pancreas is working better and your
body is responding to that insulin
better. Therefore, you need less
insulin. That's that's what that all
means. Over here, you see blood pressure
goes down, oxidative stress goes down,
meaning less inflammation, all that less
damage. Appetite in the evening, you
guys. Appetite.
You're eating less in the evening and
yet your appetite goes down.
How could it be? You're eating less and
yet you're not even eating in the
evening. You're fasting in the evening.
How is that possible? You're not eating
and yet your appetite has gone down.
Interesting. Right now, I want you to
notice here that the there's a red arrow
because it appears to be negative. That
the triglycerides go up.
triglycerides go up. Fasting
triglycerides go up. I want to tell you
why that happens. That happens because
people are losing weight.
And so when people lose weight,
and in this case, what's happening is
that they're in what's called the fat
oxidation.
Fat oxidation means you're burning fat
and you're an extended fast when so the
fasting triglycerides when they measure
the triglycerides in the morning they
this is after an extended fat fast as
after an extended fast of 18 hours
people have are burning fat at that
moment they're in fat oxidation so
what's happening in many people is that
these fats these triglycerides these uh
fatty acids ids are mobilized. They're
burning fat at that moment. So when they
prick their fingers, they measure their
triglycerides,
the fats are at that moment mobilized in
their body. In other words, they're in
fat oxy. They're burning fat at the
moment. So when they measure their
triglycerides, the fats are in their
blood. They're they're being used as as
fuel in that moment. That's the that's
the theory anyway. That's why the and
what happens is while their weight while
they're losing weight their
triglycerides are elevated. Um but when
the weight is stabilizes their
triglycerides come back down and then
they stabilize as well. So while they're
losing weight their triglycerides are
higher fasting triglycerides are higher
and then they come back down. Okay. Uh I
want to show you here the what happens
with the glucose. I'm going to skip this
one because what I really want to show
you is this. This was what happens. The
dark bars are the people who are fasting
and the white bars are the people who
don't fast. And look at what happening
over here. Look at every single one of
these comparisons. The desire to eat,
especially look at the evening. Okay,
the desire to eat in the evening.
The dark bar is the fasting people. The
group that's fasting. The desire to eat
in the evening is lower in the people
who are fasting. The desire to eat in
the evening. These are the people who
are fasting in the evening. And yet
their desire to eat is lower for those
who are fasting in the evening. Same
with their capacity to eat.
Same with their hunger.
The people who are fasting
are less hungry than the people who are
not fasting.
How is that possible? You guys,
not only that, look at the two bottom
ones.
Look at the evening fullness, you guys.
Are you looking at this? Are you seeing
what I'm seeing?
No, for reals.
How is it possible that a person who is
fasting
is more full
in the evening
than a person who is not fasting
for reals I'm just asking
and specifically stomach fullness in the
evening is more in the person who's
fasting who
Supposedly their stomach is empty
if they're fasting and yet they feel
more stomach fullness
than the person who's not fasting.
Explain to me
how's that possible?
You want to know?
Have you ever heard of a medication
that's super popular right now called
Ompic
Wiggoi?
GLP1.
They cost like $1,000 a month. Have you
Has anyone ever heard of those? Put a
put a one into chat
if you've heard of these expensive
medications that everybody's on.
Everybody's losing weight. It's like
$1,000 a month.
If your insurance doesn't cover it, that
is if you're lucky enough, your
insurance covers it, right?
Unfortunately, if you get off the
medication,
you gain all the way back the minute
you're off the medication. They do have
some side effects. A lot, actually.
Have you heard of them? If you have, put
a one in the chat, please.
They're called GLP-1 medications because
of the appetite hormone they control.
A one. We have a one.
We have another one. So, some of you
have heard of this. I just want I have
some ones in the chat. All right.
Sharon, Valerie, and May. Thank you very
much, you guys. I just want to show you
what intermittent fasting, specifically
early timerestricted eating, can do to
your appetite hormones. You guys,
not only GLP1, which is right here in
the corner. You see it? GLP, GLP1.
Also, grein, leptin, and P Y. These are
all appetite hormones, you guys.
Wow.
My doctor asked me, was I on that
medication? I told him no. It's not in
his chart. Lol. Told him I drink lemon
water. Awesome, Denise. Good for you. I
presume he asked you because you've been
losing weight
and and he asked you because of that and
you said no, you've been uh drinking
lemon water. Good for you. Awesome.
Good for you. Okay. Well, I just want to
show you. So, lots of ones over here.
Kenny and Ve and Denise. All right. You
guys watch
intermittent fasting can improve your
appetite hormones.
That's why we saw what we saw in the
previous slide. You're less hungry in
the evening. You feel more fullness.
More fullness at the people who do eat
because of this.
Because of this,
there's more.
The only one that that doesn't really
make sense is the leptin because there's
a tiny little bit of less leptin in the
evening, but there's also less grein,
which is the appetite stimulating
hormone. There's more P Y and there's
more GLP1. So, the combination of all of
it is that there's less appetite in the
evening. As we saw in that other
previous slide, the combination of all
these changes is less appetite in the
evening. There it is. Yes. Okay. So,
that's what that doctor asked you,
Denise. All right. Great. So, you're
giving them a good example.
So, if you don't want to go on those
expensive medications, here's another
option for you.
do t r e timerestricted eating. I've
been doing it for 5 years. It's so hard
for me to eat in the evening. I get a
stomach ache. I literally can't eat.
Cannot eat. Cannot. That's why honestly
you guys, it says right here, oops, went
too far. Capacity to eat. Do you see
right there? Top middle.
When I go with my family for
Thanksgiving,
I have to take major amounts of charcoal
that day after the dinner because
I can't eat. It's hard you guys. After
some time of dinner, it's hard. You
can't eat capacity to eat. It goes down.
You can't do it. I'm just saying. I'm
telling you. Your A1C went down. What
are the best time to eat? It depends.
May it depends on your own schedule. So,
if you get up at 6, well, you're going
to have to eat early. But if you get up
at 9, you know, so it depends. It
depends on your schedule. But they say,
I think the best time to eat is within
an hour of getting up. So, it depends on
what time you get up, what time you go
to bed. So, if you get up, if you go to
bed some some like my uncle goes to bed
at 8:00 p.m. So, he would need to eat at
different times that I I go to bed
around 10:00. So, you know, it depends
on what time you get up and you go to
bed. But within an hour of going or
getting up, have your first meal and
then the next meal, maybe about five to
6 hours after that. And um you know, if
you're going to have a three meal
schedule, maybe that's a little
different, but your next meal should be
5 to 6 hours after that if you're going
to do two two meals. So, and so your
your eating window should be 6 to eight
hours more or less. More or less. So,
that's that's what they recommend here.
This was a six-hour eating window. So, I
wanted to show you this also. Prolonged
overnight fast reduces cancer. Why?
Because we saw how cancer is connected
to inter uh to the insulin resistance.
That's basically what's going on here.
So, it reduces uh the glucose. It
benefits glucose control in other words.
And that's what's improving the cancer
risk. That's it. So that's it's all
connected you guys. Here's another one.
Timerestricted feeding and potential for
type 2 diabetes melodies. Type two
diabetes in other words. And what does
it say later in this study right there?
says time TRF that's timerestricted
feeding as a longterm uh adjunct
treatment may be an effective safe and
attainable method of reducing body
weight, blood pressure and IR that means
insulin resistance in patients with type
two diabetes. Researchers suggest that
fasting may provide various health
benefits for patients diagnosed with or
hoping to prevent.
So not just with for diabetes, it's for
preventing diabetes and other chronic
metabolic diseases. So not just for
diabetes or prevention diabetes, all
other diseases that we mentioned before.
TRF, in other words, timerestricted
feeding holds potential for reducing
insulin resistance, a core defect of
type 2 diabetes that is often ignored or
undertreated. That's what we've been
saying you guys.
So look it, this is from the obesity
society is the same eating window we
talked about. 8 to two 8 to2 same eating
window obesity society. And look at what
they're saying over here. Look at the
caption right there. The little
paragraph. It says early timerestricted
feeding can increase fat. Are you
looking at it? Fat burning.
I'm not saying it. Obesity society. Fat
burning when?
Look at it.
Fat burning at night. At night.
And reduce.
Are you looking?
Hunger swings.
Do you want to reduce hunger swings?
Right there. Hunger swings.
I'm going to repeat it in case you
didn't hear it.
Early time restricted feeding can
increase fat burning at night and reduce
hunger swings.
Two key factors in losing weight.
You guys, if you do this and whole and a
whole food um um plant-based whole food
diet, there's like no way you cannot not
lose weight. You're going to lose
weight. You're going to lose weight.
It's almost 100% you're going to lose
weight. You cannot not lose weight. If
you do this and a whole food plant-based
diet, so in early time restricted
feeding, people eat their last meal
by the midafter afternoon and don't eat
again until breakfast the next morning.
That's the definition.
You're burning fat at night. That's what
it says. That's right there. Okay. So,
I'm not saying it. understand it.
And I'm just telling you again, I'm just
look. Look, that's what's going on here.
The fat in your muscles,
you're burning it at night when you're
sleeping.
Don't you want to do that? I don't know.
I'm just saying. Okay, here's another
one. Early timerestricted feeding
reduces appetite.
This isn't just one study, you guys. You
see how there's like a lot of studies
that show the same thing. Reduces
appetite and increases what? Look.
Fat oxidation. What does that mean?
Burning. Burning. Fat oxidation.
Okay. So there's confirmation.
Now look look look.
Meal frequency and timing are associated
with changes in body mass index in
Adventist health study.
Oo,
this is cool. I just want to look just
want to read it for you. Adventist
health study 2. It showed I'm just going
to go down to the results. It shows a
subjects who ate one or two meals. I
recommend two, not one, had a reduction
in body mass index per year. And they
tell you how much blah blah blah
compared to those who ate three. In
other words, those who ate two lost more
weight.
Um, da da da da. Okay, I'm going to go
straight to breakfast eaters experience
a decreased
body mass index compared to breakfast
skippers. Don't skip breakfast. Relative
to subjects who ate their largest meal
at dinner, those who consume breakfast
as their largest meal experience a
significant decreased BMI. Eat your
largest meal for breakfast.
Conclusion.
Our results suggest that in a relatively
healthy and relatively healthy adults
eating less frequently, not more
frequently, less frequently.
No snacking. Did you hear no snacking?
Consuming breakfast and eating the
largest meal in the morning
may be effective methods for preventing
long-term weight gain. eating breakfast
and lunch five to six hours apart and
making the overnight fast
last
18 or 19 hours may be useful practical
strategy
it's just the study I'm not saying it
the study showed it okay this was health
study adventist health study in other
words this is people who lived in
Luminda mostly but other adventists in
California and other parts in the
country now this study
Just to show you, okay, this is just a
comparison.
This study also studied early time or
not not early but also did the
timerestricted eating. But in this
study, the people started eating at
noon.
This is just for comparison you guys. In
this study, the people started eating at
noon
and finished eating at 8. And what were
their results?
not more effective in weight loss
with this kind of schedule. No more
effective in weight loss than eating
throughout the day. They didn't find
anything. In other words, wasn't
effective. Why? Because it's not in
harmony with the circadian rhythm, you
guys. This is not how our body is made
up. This is not in harmony with how we
are designed. Our circadian rhythm is
made so that we can eat early. In fact,
look at this study. It says circadian
clock circadian rhythm is the rhythm of
day and night. This is how God designed
us to eat earlier. This is why this
study says circadian rock uh clock and
insulin resistance. And if you go down
uh further down the bottom, it says
glucose tolerance is higher in the
morning.
Your body processes the food better in
the morning than in the evening. So
whatever you eat in the evening is going
to make your glucose go up, but whatever
you eat earlier in the day, you can
process it better. That's what it says
right here.
That's what our bodies are designed to
eat earlier. Your glucose tolerance is
better earlier. That's what it's
showing. Now, one more thing I wanted to
show you about circadian rhythm, meaning
day and night, light and darkness. And
this is what I was telling you about Dr.
Schwelt.
I think he showed this probably he
showed this because I think I've seen it
from him.
But exposure to sunlight reduces glucose
levels
and it has to do with your mitochondria
which are the little furnaces inside of
the cell. These are little organels
inside of the cell that basically burn
energy. Well, they work better when we
expose oursel to sunlight. But here is
talking about the infrared energy from
the sun. So, you don't even have to
expose your uh skin necessarily to the
ultraviolet rays. We're not talking
about getting uh burned necessarily by
the sun. It's just getting the warmth.
You can even have your sleeves all the
way down. You don't even have to expose
the skin. Just the warmth. And in fact,
now they even sell these red lights. And
now everybody's talking about the red
lights. These are the mitochondria, by
the way. The little thingies you see
those are these are the muscle cells, of
course. But the mitochondria are those
little furnaces inside the organels that
use up that make energy. But now you see
red light therapy. Everybody's doing red
light therapy and you have to buy these
lights. You don't have to buy the
lights, you guys. The sun gives you the
infrared
light uh the infrared uh uh energy. It
comes from the sun. All you have to do
is get out into outside basically into
the the light of the sun and just be
outside for a few minutes. Just feel the
warmth of the sun. That's all. That's
it. And you get the same benefits of the
red light therapy. And it says right
here, significantly improve blood sugar
levels. It's all over the place. Just
Google it or whatever other engine uh
search engine. Okay. The last thing I
want to mention is the microbiota, which
as you know is the healthy
uh flora, the healthy microbes in the
gut. And now we know how important they
are. We used to think bacteria were all
bad. Now we know that we can't live
without it. Actually, we need the
healthy bacteria in our gut. And for
that, we need to feed it. And look, look
at what this says. It says right here
that diabetics in general, their
microbiota is way less healthy. In fact,
it says that right here that people with
diabetes have different uh type or
different microbiota than healthy
people. And the early differences in
microbiota composition
uh are can be diagnostic markers in fact
for people with type 2 diabetes. The
differences in composition of species
and microorganisms in the gut and
environmental factors may predict an
individual's evolution towards obesity
and diabetes since childhood. I that's
kind of scary. So whatever we do even
since childhood can put us at higher
risk. Uh you know and that could be what
we're exposed to even from birth. In
fact, in a Mediterranean diet, which is
a very planttheavy diet, that's what one
of the um one of the things about the
Mediterranean diet that you eat a lot of
beans, you eat a lot of vegetables. It
says right here, "Our results suggest
that long-term consumption of the
Mediterranean diet
uh and the low-fat high that's what LH
uh LFHCC that's a lowfat high complex
carbohydrate diet exert a positive
effect in the development of type 2
diabetes by different specific changes
in the gut microbiota increasing the
abundance of these different types of
really good um micro micro ropes
basically that make your microbiota
healthier because they have more fiber.
That's what feeds your microbiota. The
fiber
uh it says right here the consumption of
resistant starch that's a type of starch
but it actually works like fiber. You
don't digest this kind of starch
and improves insulin sensitivity. So
where do you find this kind of starch
resistant starch? Do you know? Do you
know where this starch is found?
You want to know? Well, look. These are
foods that have resistant starch. Did
you know? So, a lot of people asked me
this at camp meeting last week, and in
fact, I said yes, it's true. You can
boil potatoes
and rice. Same thing with rice. You can
boil the potatoes. You can boil the rice
and let them cool down.
Did you know this?
Cool them down and the amount of
resistant starch goes up and then you
warm them up and then they actually have
more resistant starch. I don't know if
you knew this, but it is true. Oh,
somebody says, "Besides praying, how how
can I help a diabetic that doesn't want
to follow a correct diet?" Well, I mean,
you can share some of this information
because you know what? You can start
moving them along that spectrum, those
steps of change. Sometimes people are in
the pre-contemplated, what's called the
pre-contemplated stage, and they don't
want to hear anything. And but the more
they hear, maybe they're slowly,
you don't even realize, but slowly
slowly they're start contemplating
making those changes. So the more the
more the more you you and actually if
they see you as a model for those
changes the better. So and actually it
doesn't have good nutrition doesn't do
any good exercise you can maybe share
some kind of uh good
uh dish with them. Maybe bring them some
healthy cookie or something like that. I
don't know. I'm just making up things.
bring uh share shared them a a link to
or maybe even watch it with them like a
good documentary, Forks Over Nights,
What the Health, one of those really
life-changing documentaries, if they're
open to it, because sometimes just
watching one of those things can change
somebody's life. You would you would be
surprised. People sometimes just
watching one of those things, they're
like, "Wow, this is it. I'm changing my
life." Something like that. uh watching
you make those uh changes sometimes just
being a role model for people. So did
you eat say eat those cold? No, you let
them cool. The starches in those will
change. So the from regular starch to
resistant starch and then you can
actually heat them up and the resistant
starch will uh will still be there. So
just by letting them cool down once, it
will then change the composition of the
resist of the starches. So you could
warm them up again, but the potatoes and
the rice can actually change the
composition. Uh so these are some of the
uh sources of resistant starch. As you
can see, green bananas, lentils, beans.
Um yeah, you're welcome, Reuben. Yeah,
no problem. So again, see these are some
uh but you can of course Google this um
and you can get more ideas of sources of
resistant starch. But you probably have
also heard of probiotics and probiotics
are the actual micro uh microbes, right?
The actual good bacteria.
Prebiotics
are the food that actually feeds the
good bacteria. And I'll tell you what,
they have found some they've done some
studies that have found that probiotics
don't always work, especially the
supplements.
Some for some people they take the
probiotics, they don't stick. And they
were doing a lot of uh you know the
giving probiotics especially for people
who take antibiotics
and they were even giving the um you
know like prescription pro uh probiotics
for people and not always work. They
don't always work, but I'll tell you
what, prebiotics
will most likely work because you will
start feeding the little microbes again
and they can recolonize
uh your gut if you're having to take
antibiotics. Hopefully, you won't have
to do that. But even if you have a lot
of gut issues, there's a lot of people
with uh IBS, the irritable bowel
syndrome,
a lot of people with other types of gut
issues. A lot of that has to do with
something called disbiosis,
meaning your gut bacteria is not
healthy.
You know that gut bacteria uh issues
start from birth. In fact, if you have
been b uh if you were born by C-section,
you already started off at a
disadvantage because babies that are
born through the birth canal, they get
inoculated with the mother's bacteria
through the birth canal. So, babies who
don't go through that are already at a
disadvantage. Not that they can't
recover, but the babies born through
regular vaginal birth already get at the
advantage of being inoculated with the
moms. um bacteria going through the
birth canal. also being breastfed
advantage because they're getting you
know some of the u advantages of being
breastfed you know the good bacteria the
formula not so of course once they start
eating solid food
vegetables the fruits the foods with uh
fiber if the babies are eating you know
the baby food the chicken or whatever no
fiber and of course then they start
eating the uh junk food, forget it. So
all of this, you know, the the the
people who are the who are raised on
nothing but meat and potatoes are going
to have very different gut bacteria that
the people who are raised on beans and
vegetables. Okay? So this could be a
lifelong issue for a lot of people. And
so this can lead to a lifelong problem
called disbiosis.
And so this can lead to lifelong gut
issues. Uh IBS being one of them. IBD
uh can be inflammatory bowel disease
such as Crohn's disease can be even even
more serious as you probably know. So
are fermented foods good for us to eat?
Yes. Uh I would say yes.
But don't rely on that. just the only
source of good gut health. I would say
that could be a good source of
probiotics.
But don't rely on it as and I would say
as long as they're non-dairy. So right
here you have non-dairy yogurt for
instance. I wouldn't do dairy yogurt
just because you would be putting too
many animal proteins in the in the body.
I would prefer non-dairy with no sugar.
So, as as long as they are like the ones
you see right here, uh these are good
sources. The kimchi, as long as it
doesn't have too much salt, that kind of
thing. So, make sure you're looking for
the healthy uh versions of these
probiotic foods. But what I also want to
make sure is that I mentioned that you
also want to make sure you're eating
more prebiotics
because as long as you're feeding the
good bacteria, you can probably solve
the disbiosis problem and you are going
to always be feeding the good bacteria
and that's better. How do you eat tempe?
Excellent question. I always put it on a
pan without oil or you can actually put
it in the oven or air fryer with some uh
seasonings like a little bit of soy
sauce or bra uh liquids aminos that's
even better. Um but whatever seasonings
you want and uh and I eat it with uh
brown you can eat it brown rice you can
eat it with some kind of noodles uh
vegetables.
It's very similar to tofu. You can
prepare it with very similar to tofu and
stir fry it. I I never use oil. I use it
with other things, but very similar to
tofu. That's what I would say. It's very
delicious, actually. Very, very
delicious. Uh so, I highly recommend it.
Okay, you guys. But this is why I
recommend eat a whole food plant-based
diet. As long as you're eating a whole
food plant-based diet, you will be
eating a lot of the fibers, a lot of the
prebiotics, a lot of the resistant
starches, and naturally getting enough
fiber. Most people are fiber deficient.
When people ask you, "Where do you get
your protein?" If you're like eating a
vegetarian or, you know, whole
plant-based diet and people ask you,
"Where do you get your protein?" you go
ahead and ask them, "Well, where do you
get your fiber?" Because you're probably
fiber deficient. The average fiber
intake in this country is like 15 grams
a day, and most people need like 30 to
35. And to be healthy, you mo you should
be getting more like 50 grams. I get
like 50 or 60 grams a day most times. Uh
so most people are going to be very
short of that. So when people ask you,
"Where do you get your proteins?" You
just answer, "Where do you get your
fiber?" And that's it.
you'll be you'll be uh you'll be better.
So, um I'm going to give you my website
again because as you know I have a 10day
challenge in my website health4day.net.
I want to tell you guys that I just
finished a round in my work for people
who did 10 days of whole food
plant-based diet. And I'm going to tell
you, a lot of people don't do it 100%.
Um, and even so, a lot of people follow
it like 90 to 95%. And I had, for
instance, one, I'm not going to give you
the real names, okay? But I had a person
whose glucose I have the paper right
here, but I'm not going to give you the
right the name for privacy, but I had a
lady and she's from church. She started
off with 137. She's been diabetic for
years. She started off with glucose at
and last Sunday was the last day of our
10day challenge. She finished with 118.
She's below the glucose threshold. So,
she is now in the pre-diabetes
range as opposed to diabetes. And her
blood pressure went from 133 over 79 to
122 over 75. and she lost four pounds.
Her cholesterol was already good when
she went from 153 to 126. That's
wonderful. And her LDL was okay. It was
above 70. Since she's a diabetic, she
should have been below uh below 70. So,
she was at 88 and now she's at 63, you
guys. So, she's wonderful. So, that's in
10 days. Okay. We have another person
who's um let's see triglycerides
way too high. They were at 214 and in 10
days they lowered it to 141. That you
want to be below 150. So now perfect
triglycerides. All right. We had one
person whose cholesterol was 210 and in
10 days they lowered it to 188 you guys.
And their LDL was 120, they lowered it
to 101. So, they're almost there. They
should be below 100, but 101, hey,
they're they're pretty darn close. So,
that's wonderful. And they lost two
pounds. Uh, we have a a person whose
cholesterol was 131. Now, they're below
100. So, our our machine doesn't even
doesn't even measure it because we have
a a small little machine that below 100
doesn't even it doesn't register. And
their uh blood pressure was pretty high
because they're um hypertensive. So, it
was 143 over 81. Now we're at 133 over
79. Woohoo. So no longer hypertensive.
Uh cholesterol, this other person 204.
Now they're 173.
Their LDL, you guys watch. Or here
actually listen to me. Their LDL
121.
That's so high. You definitely need a
statin. Now it's 50. 50. Oh my goodness.
So that's just wonderful. That that's
just just very very good. Um this person
had a glucose of 132 to start to end
104.
132 104
is another diabetic to pre-diabetic.
Wow. Okay. This is the last one I wanted
to share with you. The total cholesterol
went from 169 to 145. So 169 is not high
but it went down even lower. The
triglycerides were went from 146 to 129.
Those were all very good. Um
so everything is pretty good in this
person. The pre blood pressure was 123
over 70 78 to 104 over 66. I mean, this
is this is already a kind of healthy
person who went from kind of healthy to
super healthy. And their uh weight has
been consistently going down. So, this
person's like the third time they do
this program. So, this time their weight
went from 220 to 218. So, they lost
another two pounds. It's like the third
time they do the program. So, I mean,
they've just been improving uh very very
much. Okay. Okay, so last person uh
cholesterol went from 182 to 177, LDL
119 to 113. So just small uh drop a drop
nonetheless. Uh glucose 103 to 100. So
small drop, but blood pressure 143 over
85 to 128 over 77. And um she lost two
pounds. So So anyway, we have a lot of
cases like that every time. So what I
wanted to tell you is that in 10 days
you can do it. So you can um download
the 10day challenge also from this
website health fortoday.net
and it is right here. 10day challenge.
Just go in there. I don't even ask you
for your uh email, nothing. Just
download the PDF right there. Boom.
10day challenge. Daniel Daniel
challenge. By the way, also if there's
anyone who uh is Spanish speaking, I
never say it forget to say it, but I do
have a Spanish website and there it is.
Salutaro.com
and it's the whole thing is also
available in Spanish. All right, so
we're out of time. I am going to uh pray
you guys. Sorry, there's no more time
for uh questions, but we've been
answering them all along. So, I'm going
to pray. I'm going to tell you when is
our next program, and I'm going to talk
about
building better habits, how to do it,
and how to increase um
uh how to increase self uh control. And
our next program is August 19th. Okay?
And I think you're going to have a
program, Dr. Schwelt, next week. Don't
miss it. It's going to be great. Okay.
Uh, does your cookbook come in English?
Yes, I have a cookbook in English. Just
look it up under my name on Amazon. And
I you might be able to go into my
website and get a direct link to my
Amazon cookbook from my website. Uh, and
if I don't have that, I should add it.
So, I'll add it this week if I haven't
added it, but it's on Amazon. So yes, my
cookbook is in English. So let's pray
you guys. Let's finish with a nice
prayer. Okay. Dear heavenly father,
thank you so much for everything you
give us. All your blessings are new
every day. And we ask you to forgive us
because sometimes we don't take proper
care of our bodies. And we just ask you
to forgive us and to make us new
creatures and give us wisdom and
understanding in your Holy Spirit so
that we can have self-control so we can
have the fruit of your Holy Spirit in
us. and give us the strength and the
wisdom
and the ability to
take proper care of this body temple and
also to what we have learned to also
share it with other people so that other
people may get to know you better to
know that you are our maker and our
savior and our healer. Help us to be uh
good representatives of you wherever we
go to take this message of healing
everywhere. Um and to take it to all
people that we may know
so that we may be your ambassadors
wherever we go.
And be with us rest of this day and the
rest of this week. and uh be with every
single person who is connected tonight
and who will watch this program in
Jesus' name we pray. Amen.
Thank you again you guys. Thank you
everyone who has connected and uh we ask
you to like this video to share it to uh
subscribe to this channel to turn on
your notifications and to connect
tomorrow. There's more programming on
Wednesdays and on Sabbath, of course.
So, make sure you are always notified
when the next program is coming up. So,
thank you so much again. Thank you for
everything uh that that you guys do for
us and thank you for sharing our
programs and Amen. Amen. Amen. Thank you
again. Thank you for being with us and
God bless you and please share this
program. Thank you again you guys.